Preliminary Guide to the Edwin Harrison Cady Papers, 1858-2000 (bulk 1961-2000) RL.00182
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edwin Harrison Cady papers
1858-2000, bulk circa 1961-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cady, Edwin Harrison
RL.00182
44.3 Linear Feet
26,881 items
Access Restrictions
Some of the materials in this collection are not immediately accessible because they require further processing before use.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Edwin Harrison Cady Papers were a gift to Duke University, 1992-2002.
Biographical Note
Edwin Harrison Cady, educator and writer, was born in Old Tappan, N. J. He was educated at Ohio Wesleyan University, the University of Cincinnati, and the University of Wisconsin. He has taught at the University of Wisconsin, Ohio State University, Indiana University, Syracuse University, and Duke University where he was Andrew Mellon Professor of English. He was been a visiting professor at the Royal University at Uppsala and the University of Stockholm, Sweden. His interests, other than American literature, were sports and music. He was editor of American Literature from 1980 to 1986, and was a prominent scholar on the life and writings of William Dean Howells.
Collection Overview
The papers consist of correspondence from Jay B. Hubbell and John Olin Eidson. The Eidson letters (5 items) discuss the upcoming program of the American Literature Section of the Modern Language Association of America and suggest Richard Armour as the featured speaker. The letters are arranged chronologically.
Accession (1992-0127) (20,000 items, 30.0 lin. ft.) includes correspondence, research and teaching notes, writings, student offprints, card files, photostats, materials relating to the Center for Editions of American Authors, files relating to American Literature, printed matter, clippings, and other miscellaneous items. Correspondence includes letters from Jay B. Hubbell and John O. Eidson; the latter concern the American Literature Section of the Modern Language Association.
Accession (2002-0104), dated 1858-2000 (1251 items; 6.8 linear feet) primarily comprises materials related to writings by Cady and his former student Thomas F. O'Donnell regarding author, editor, and critic William Dean (W.D.) Howells. In 2000, Cady edited and wrote an introduction to a volume of Howells' poetry entitled Pebbles, Monochromes, and Other Modern Poems, 1891-1916, and his collection holds various drafts of this work as well as correspondence between Cady and his publishers concerning the book's publication. Also included is material written by or collected by Cady or O'Donnell while editing or writing other books and articles regarding Howells' poetry; and original correspondence from Howells to his publishers.
Accession (2010-0083) (300 items; 7.5 lin. ft.) includes books by and about William Dean Howells, most with annotations by Edwin Cady and Harry H. Clark, as well as materials (first proofs, drafts, and other Howells publications) that were used by Cady in the preparation of Howells' complete works. Books date from approximately 1881-1981; manuscript materials date from approximately 1879-1992.
Related Material
For more information, see the Thomas Francis O'Donnell Papers, 1940-1978, in the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Microfilms; Scholars -- United States -- Correspondence; College teachers as authors; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Criticism and interpretation; American literature -- History and criticism; Poetry, Modern -- 19th century -- History and criticism; Literary historians -- United States; American poetry -- 19th century; American literature -- Study and teaching; Color photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Modern Language Association of America. American Literature Section; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920 -- Criticism and interpretation; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920 -- Correspondence; Hubbell, Jay B. (Jay Broadus), 1885-1979; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920; Cady, Edwin Harrison; Cady, Edwin Harrison; Eidson, John O.; Center for Editions of American Authors
- Accessions (5-14-82) and (1992-0127)
  - Correspondence: Aaron, Dan - Fryckstedt, O. - Materials pertaining to American Literature (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Gibson, William - Marsden, Malcolm (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Martin, Jay - Stahr, Elvis (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Stephens, Martha - Zerrnan, Bill (Box 4)
  - Center for Editions of American Authors (Correspondence, minutes, etc., 1961-1966) (Box 4)
  - Howells, William Dean, articles on (Arranged alphabetically by author's surname) (Box 5-6)
  - Howells, William Dean, copies of articles by (Box 6-7)
  - Howells, William Dean: Materials pertaining his relationship to other writers, correspondence with Howells, and copies of short writings (Box 7-8)
  - Howells, William Dean: Books and materials relevant to his published works (Box 9)
  - Howells, William Dean: Special topics (Box 10)
  - Family materials, albums, and correspondence (Box 11)
  - Teaching notes (Alphabetically arranged by author or subject) (Box 12-13)
  - Miscellaneous files (Box 13)
  - Materials pertaining to the publications of On Dickinson, On Emerson, On Frost, On Whitman, and miscellanea (Box 14)
  - Miscellanea pertaining to the Growth of American Literature, and reviews (Box 15)
  - Articles, drafts, and off prints (Generally arranged by author's surname.) (Box 16)
  - Cady, Young Howells and John Brown: Episodes in a Radical Education (Draft); Cady, Critical Essays on William Dean Howells Through the 1920s (Original and Xerox copies); On Dickinson; miscellanea (Box 17)
  - Lectures by Cady (2 tapes); vertical file on authors; Cady, Young Howells and John Brown: Episodes in a Radical Education (Draft) (Box 18)
  - Writings by Cady, and published journals (Box 19)
  - Cady, The Big Game, related materials; Nixon archive (1 folder); and miscellanea (Box 20)
  - Student offprints, writings by Josephine Piercy, and bibliographic note cards (Box 21)
  - Cady, Critical Essays on William Dean Howells, (Galley), correspondence, Modern Instance (Draft), and miscellanea (Box 22)
  - Photostats of 19th century newspapers (Box 23)
  - Writings (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, Hubbell center materials, and miscellanea (Box 25)
  - William M. Gibson Papers (Center for Editions of American Authors) (Box 26)
  - John Woolman: The Mind of the Quaker Saint (Drafts of chapters, correspondence, volume, etc.) (Box 27)
  - Center for Editions of American Authors materials, football materials, and miscellanea (Box 28)
  - Blank American Literature stationery (Box 29)
  - The Big Game (Notes and drafts) (Box 30)
- Accession (2002-0104)
  - Cady's writings (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Included here are various drafts of Cady's Introduction to his edited volume of W.D. Howells' poetry, Pebbles Monochromes, and Other Modern Poems, 1891-1916. Also included are some of Cady's notes related to this work.
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    Includes incoming correspondence to Cady offering critiques of his Introduction; correspondence between Cady and his publisher (Ohio University Press); and copies of original correspondence between Howells and his publishers (dating from 1895-1905).
  - Cady's writings (Box 2)
    Additional drafts of Cady's Introduction to his edited volume of Howells poetry; drafts of Cady's footnotes.
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence from publishers and editors to Cady; correspondence between Cady and other writers; and some personal correspondence.
  - Correspondence (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence to and from Thomas F. O'Donnell (Cady's former graduate student) regarding his work on a volume of Howells' poetry and correspondence related to earlier Howells projects of Cady and others. Also includes correspondence between Cady and other professors and copies of original correspondence to and from Howells regarding his writing (dating from 1909-1918).
  - Checklists of Howells' published poetry (Box 3)
  - Bulletins and progress reports (Box 3)
    Related to O'Donnell's work on his volume of Howells' poetry.
  - O'Donnell's writings (Box 4)
    Includes drafts of O'Donnell's Introduction to his edited volume, The Complete Poems of William Dean Howells. Also includes notes on Howells.
  - Correspondence (Box 4)
    Includes letters to and from O'Donnell relating to his volume of Howells' poetry; correspondence from O'Donnell explaining his expenses incurred while working on his Howells project; and copies of original correspondence to and from Howells (dating from 1858 to 1917).
  - Checklists of Howells' published poetry (Box 4)
  - O'Donnell's writings (Box 5)
    Includes drafts of O'Donnell's Introduction to his volume of Howells' poetry. Also includes notes on Howells.
  - Howells' writings (Box 5)
    Includes copies of Howells' poems as well as a copy of Howells' Modern Italian Poets, 1887
  - Correspondence (Box 5)
    Includes letters related to O'Donnell's search for copies of Howells' poems, and letters between O'Donnell and his editors.
  - Howells' writings (Box 6)
    Includes copies of Howells poems (copies of original handwritten poems as well as typed versions).
  - Cady's writings (Box 7)
    Drafts of Cady's speech A Generation in American Editing (1964) is included.
  - O'Donnell's writings (Box 7)
    Includes a draft of O'Donnell's Introduction to his volume on Howells' poetry.
  - Howells' writings (Box 7)
  - Cady's writings (Box 8)
    Includes various papers, speeches and other short works by Cady. Also includes related correspondence.
  - Cady's writings (Box 9)
    Includes various papers, speeches and other short works by Cady. Also includes related correspondence and notes.
  - Cady's writings (Box 10)
    Includes various papers, speeches and other short works by Cady. Also includes some related correspondence and notes.
  - Howells' writings (Box 10)
  - Howells' writings (Box 11)
    Includes copies of numerous Howells poems (copies of original handwritten poems as well as typed versions). Also includes 1 microfilm reel.
  - Other writings (Box 12)
    Includes studies of Howells by various authors.
    - Notes from Cady's work on Howells (Box 12)
    - Draft of a letter to a fellow professor (Box 12)
    - Drafts of Cady's jacket copy for his volume on Howells' poetry (Box 12)
- Accession (2010-0083), 1881-1982, 5 boxes
  Acc. (2010-0083) (300 items; 7.5 lin. ft.) includes books by and about William Dean Howells, most with annotations by Edwin Cady and Harry H. Clark, as well as materials (first proofs, drafts, and other Howells publications) that were used by Cady in the preparation of Howells' complete works. Books date from approximately 1881-1981; manuscript materials date from approximately 1879-1992.
  - Books by and about William Dean Howells (Box 1-4)
  - Facsimile of The Editor's Study, ed. by James W. Simpson, 1886-1892 (Box 4)
  - Photograph album with photographic copies of William Dean Howells and his family (Box 4)
  - Pictures of Howells: photographic copies, slides, negatives, and correspondence relating to these images, 1950s (Box 4)
  - Altrurian Romances-Master Record Text facsimile, 1892-1893 (Box 5)
  - William Dean Howells: An American Life, Kenneth S. Lynn, 1971 (Box 5)
  - William Dean Howells, Pioneer et Coordinateur du mouvement realiste American, 1837-1920, Jean Riviere, undated (3 versions) (Box 5)
  - April Hopes, Harper's New Monthly Magazine, undated (Box 5)
  - An Imperative Duty, Harper's New Monthly Magazine, undated (Box 5)
  - Bibliography of William Dean Howells, New York Public Library, 1946 (Box 5)
  - Editor's Study, 1886-1891 (Box 5)
  - The Landlord at Lion's Head, First Proofs, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Interviews with Howells (Box 5)
  - Howells' autograph, 1879 (Box 5)
  - Howells' holographs (2), 1899 and 1900 (Box 5)
  - A Hazard of New Fortunes (television series) proposals and scripts, 1990-1992 (Box 5)
  - Cady correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 5)